<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
			 "/home/arl/lib/docbk/dtd/docbookx.dtd">

<article lang="en">

<articleinfo>
   <title>MOM4 Quickstart Guide</title>

   <abstract>
   <para>
     Brief instructions for running MOM4 experiments
   </para>
   </abstract>

   <author>
     <firstname>Giang</firstname>
     <surname>Nong</surname>
     <email>Giang.Nong@noaa.gov</email>
   </author>
</articleinfo>


<section id="source code and scripts">
   <title>Get the source code and scripts through CVS checkout or download</title>
   <para>
     After you do CVS checkout successfully a directory will be created. For
     convenience, this directory will be referred to as the
     <filename>ROOT</filename> directory. A readme file in the
     <filename>ROOT</filename> directory will tell you the contents of each
     subdirectory under <filename>ROOT</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
     In the sections below, <filename>test_case</filename> is a generic name
     referring to the name of a specific experiment you are working on. Thus,
     <filename>test_case</filename> in the path
     <filename>ROOT/exp/test_case</filename> should be replaced by a concrete
     name (for example <filename>test1</filename>, <filename>test2</filename>
     , etc.) 
   </para>   
</section>


<section id="Prepare preprocessing data">
   <title>Prepare preprocessing data</title>
   <para>
     There are two ways of creating data for MOM4 experiments. The easy way is
     to get data from NOMADS server. The hard (but more independent) way is to
     create data from scratch.
   </para>
     <section id="Get data via NOMADS server">
      <title>Get data via NOMADS server</title>
      <para>
       Users first need to create directory preprocessing for each test case:
       <programlisting>
         mkdir ROOT/exp/test_case/preprocessing
       </programlisting>
       The data files in NOMADS are organized in directories having the same
       name as name of <filename>test_case</filename> (data for
       <filename>test1</filename> are in directory <filename>test1</filename>,
       etc.). Go to the experiment of your interest (see
       "Brief description of MOM4 experiments" in the MOM4 manual) and start
       downloading file <filename>preprocessing.tar</filename> to
       <filename>ROOT/exp/test_case/preprocessing</filename>. You will need to
       uncompress the file <filename>preprocessing.tar</filename> after
       downloading. The command for uncompressing a .tar file is:
       <programlisting>
       tar -xvf filename.tar
       </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>  
       Additional note for experiments test4 and test5:
       In addition to all data from preprocessing directory described above
       you will also need to:
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         create a directory called <filename>data</filename> at the same level
         as <filename>ROOT/exp/test_case</filename>.
           <programlisting>
             mkdir ROOT/exp/data
             cd ROOT/exp/data
           </programlisting>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
         create 4 subdirectories inside  <filename>data</filename>:
           <programlisting>
             mkdir ice lad omip_mpi omip_ncar
           </programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          download data from the directory <filename>Data</filename> in NOMADS
          to the corresponding subdirectory in <filename>data</filename>.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Note that data in (<filename>ASCII, HISTORY, RESTART</filename>) are
      <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> needed for running experiments. They are for the
      purpose of comparing your results with results produced at GFDL.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Create data from scratch">
      <title>Create data from scratch</title>
      <para>
        Tools are provided so that users can create data from scratch. For more
        details refer to section "Setting up an experiment with MOM4"
in the manual and the code in <filename>ROOT/src/preprocessing</filename>. 
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

<section id="Compile the source code and execute the runscript">
   <title>Compile the source code and execute the runscript</title>
   <para>
     MOM4 requires that NetCDF and MPI libraries be installed on users'
     platform.
   </para>
   <para>
     MOM4 code can be compiled and run with two memory allocation schemes:
     <emphasis>DYNAMIC</emphasis> and <emphasis>STATIC</emphasis>. Almost all
     compile scripts provided here are for the <emphasis>DYNAMIC</emphasis>
     option. For the <emphasis>STATIC</emphasis> option see
     <xref linkend="Brief description of MOM4 experiments"/> below.
   </para>
   <para>
     Under <filename>ROOT/exp/test_case</filename> there is one script for both
     compile and run. All scripts have the name beginning with
     <filename>run_mom4</filename> followed by <filename>test_case</filename>
     name (<filename>test1, test2,</filename> etc.). Before executing the
     script make sure to change the platform to the platform of your computer
     system. The platform is specified by:
     <programlisting>
       set platform = sgi # this is for sgi platform
     </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
     Users may also want to change the following before starting compilation
     and execution:
     <programlisting>
       set npes = number of processors used in the run
       set days = the length of the run in days
       set months = the length of the run in months
     </programlisting>
     Those are the most basic settings for any run. Experienced users may go to
     the namelist section in the runscript to set the values for namelist
     variables. Details on namelists can be found in the corresponding Fortran
     module. 
   </para>
</section>


<section id="Examine the output">
   <title>Examine the output</title>
   <para>
     To keep the runscript simple all output files of a model run will be in
     the work directory. There are three types of output files:
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        ascii file with <filename>.fms.out</filename> extension: the
        description of the setup of the run and verbose comments printed out
        during the run.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        restart files in <filename>RESTART</filename> directory: the model
        fields necessary to initialize future runs of the model.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        history files with <filename>.nc.tar</filename> extension: output of
        the model, both averaged over specified time intervals and snapshots.
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
     The ascii file contains everything written to the screen during model
     execution. The total time for model execution as well as the times of
     separate modules are reported here. All <filename>.tar</filename> files
     should be decompressed for viewing. The decompress command is:
     <programlisting>
       tar -xvf filename.tar
     </programlisting>
   </para>
   <para>
     Users will see result files in NetCDF format. Postprocessing tools such
     as Ferret, ncview, grads or matlab can be used to view data in these
     files. 
   </para>
</section>

<section id="Brief description of MOM4 experiments">
   <title>Brief description of MOM4 experiments</title>
   <para>
     MOM4 is distributed with a set of test cases. These tests are taken from
     models used at GFDL for testing the numerical and computational integrity
     of the code.
     <warning>
       These experiments are <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> sanctioned for their
       physical relevance. They are instead provided for the user to learn how
       to run mom4, and to verify the numerical and/or computational integrity
       of the code. <emphasis>PLEASE</emphasis> do not assume that the
       experiments will run for more than the short time selected in the
       sample run scripts.
     </warning>
   </para>
   <para>
     <simplelist>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test1</filename>: flat bottom sector model with simple
         physics. This model is very small and can be easily run on a single
         workstation. It should provide the user with a basic experience of
         running mom4.
       </member>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test2</filename>: flat bottom sector model which more
         fully tests some realistic physics options. This experiment has the
         same grid as test1, but it more thoroughly exercises the various
         physics packages.
       </member>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test3A</filename>: east-west channel with open boundary
         at west. This experiment is an illustration of the open boundary
         condition capability of mom4. Tracers include potential temperature
         and salinity.
       </member>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test3B</filename>: solid wall of twice domain size as
         test3A for testing OBC. This experiment is used to verify the
         relevance of the test3A solution at early times. That is, for early
         times, the solution from test3A should agree with that from test3B.
         Tracers include potential temperature and salinity.
       </member>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test4</filename>: global tripolar grid using roughly
         3x3 resolution with 28 vertical levels and age, biotic, and cfc tracer
         packages. Coupled to GFDL sea ice model.
       </member>
       <member>
         <filename>mom4_test5</filename>: global tripolar grid using roughly
         "1-degree" resolution ocean with 50 vertical levels coupled to the
         GFDL sea ice model and forced with the German OMIP dataset. Tracers
         include potential temperature, salinity, and age.
       </member>
    <member>	
  <filename>mom4_iom</filename>: This is Indian Ocean Community Model
   version 1.0 developed for Intensive Course on Ocean Modeling held
   at CMMACS, India, October 4-14, 2004.
   </member>
     </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Experiments are based on mom4p0 branch. For increased efficiency,
      the <option>-DSTATIC_MEMORY</option> compile option allows mom4 on the
      SGI to run about twice the speed as dynamic memory
allocation. On other platforms, however, the performance of static
option may vary substantially. Notably,
      the static option requires each processor to have identical sized
      domains, and for these domains to be specified at compile time. Hence, a
      bit of algebra is required prior to compiling the experiment.
      Specifically, <option>layout</option> in <option>ocean_model_nml</option>
      namelist should be correctly set. Example of runscript for
static option is provided for just one test case (test1_static) but users
      can build compile and run scripts for other test cases based on this
      example. 
    </para>
</section>

</article>
